12 lakh health claims were filed in ICICI LBAD last year.
Now how many of these
claims did the company settle?  How much money was
given to the policy holders and how many people had to
file complaints to get the money
?  If we get this data, we
can estimate how the company's claims
performance is.  So in today's
video you are going to get answers to all these questions and
that too with the latest data.
And more importantly, this is not data from any one
city, state, union territory or any one
zone.  This is data from all over India.
That too of the latest financial year
2025-26.  If you have
any health insurance plan of ICICI LBD then today's
video is very important for you.  So
friends, before starting this video,
I want to give these three disclaimers.   First of all,
this data is only health
insurance data.
Personal accident and travel insurance
figures are not included in this.  Secondly,
what is the source of this data?  We have taken this data
directly
from the public disclosure document of the insurance company's website.
Which you can check yourself by visiting the website.
And thirdly,
whatever weighting, ranking, scoring or
grading system we have used in this video is
Insurance Impact's own research
and methodology.  And more importantly,
this video and this series is not sponsored by any insurance
company or platform or any brand.
I have brought this data for you in
very simple language with complete transparency.
So let's
start this video without any delay and
yes stay till the end of the video because
a surprise is waiting for you at the end of the video.  The
first metric
friends we will look at is the claim settlement
ratio.  That is,
how many claims were filed by the total policy holders in the last financial year
and how many of those claims were
settled by the company.  This will also
tell us how many claims have been rejected.
The higher this percentage, this ratio,
the better it is.  Before I
directly show you this percentage, this ratio.
Let us understand
how this was calculated.  The formula for claim settlement ratio
is the total number of claims settled
divided by the total claims.  That is, out of the total
claims filed, how many claims have been
settled by the company.  But
we will not directly use the total reported claims figure within this one year.
We want those claims on which the company has
taken a decision.  So
we will adjust the outstanding claims in this.
At the beginning of the financial year 2025-26, some claims
were outstanding on which decisions have been taken.
We will add them inside it.
And we will settle the outstanding claims
at the end of this financial year
so that we get the adjusted
total claims, that is, those claims on which the
company has taken a decision, only then will this
exact number be obtained.  So the total claims
that were settled in this financial year 2025-26 were
1197679
claims and the total claims filed
after adjusting the outstanding
claims were 1269499
claims and after dividing these two and
multiplying by 100, we get a
total claim settlement ratio of
94.34%.
This percentage means that out of 100
claims, 94 claims have been approved by the company
and six claims have been rejected.
If you look at it, it is very good.
But some companies may have a claim
settlement ratio of more than 95%.  If
you want to know about those companies
then stay connected with the channel.  Because
in this report card series we are going to
review the top health insurance companies in India.
Now we have seen that the claims have been
settled by a good company.  But
how much money have you given?  But out of the ₹100 of claim that
policy holders asked for,
how much money has ICICI Labord given for health claims
in 2025-26.  That ratio will be
called claims paid ratio.  Let us see
how this will be calculated.  The total amount
paid for health claims only in ICICI LBAD health insurance.  That
is ₹6470
crore.   The
total amount claimed by policy holders throughout the year is
₹7346
crore.  Please note that
we have already adjusted the outstanding amount.  Out
of this, the
total amount paid by the company is ₹470
crores.  If we divide these two figures
and multiply them by 100,
we get a claims paid ratio of
88%.  That means the company settled 94 out of 100 claims.
And if a claim of ₹100 was
asked for, the company paid ₹88 out of it.  That
means, out of 100, claims worth ₹12 have either been
rejected or money has been deducted from some claim.
Any
deductions that were claimed and the
money was not paid by the company.  That is 12%.
Now how is this 88% claims paid ratio?
This is very good.  If we look at the claims data of the
three years preceding this financial year.
You might have seen that video, in which the
claims paid ratio of most of the good companies was between 85 to 90.  If this
claims paid ratio becomes too high
then it becomes a financial
burden on the company.  But through this series
we will find out which insurance company is
giving the maximum amount of money to the policy holders.  Currently, the
claims paid ratio of ICIC LBAD is also quite good.  Now
friends, let us understand the Incurred Claim Ratio.
You will also say that there are many ratios
but it is very important to understand them.  Only through this will we know
how the company is performing.  The
Incred Claim Ratio tells us
how many rupees of claims the company has paid against the ₹100 premium collected for the policy during the entire financial year.
Because it is possible that a company may be
collecting a lot of premium
but is being very stingy in paying claims
or it is possible that a company may
not be earning any premium but is
paying a lot of claims.  So both the situations
are negative.  So let us see
what is the Incurred Claim Ratio of ICICI LBD.  The
formula for calculating ICR is quite simple.
Net incurred claims amounting to
₹6227 crore will be divided by net earned
premium.  How much premium has been earned
for this financial year?  Money from long term
policies is not considered.
Only the money received this year will be
considered.  And the amount is ₹736
crore.  We will divide these two and
multiply them by 100.  And the incurred
claims ratio is 80.49.
Now is this good or bad?  Let us understand.
Incurred Claim Ratio is a metric
that needs to be in an ideal range.
If it becomes too low, the
ideal range here is 70 to 85%.
If it falls below 70, it
means that the company is earning a good amount of money
but in return, the claim money
being given is less.  That means the company is being very
stingy.  If it exceeds 85,
it means the company is
not earning that much money.  But she is dispersing too many
claims.  Due to which the
cost of his claim will increase, expenses will increase
and due to which the premiums may also be revised.
Because the company is
not going to shrink its profits.  So ultimately it is the
policy holders who suffer the loss.
So the ideal range of ICR that I have
kept here is 70 to 85% which
is good for both the company and the policy holders and the
Incurred Claim Ratio of ICICI LBD is also
in between this ideal range.  Now friends,
comes the most important metric of this video,
that is the analysis of complaints.
What are the most common complaints related to?  You
know that most of the complaints are
regarding claims.  So
what is the way to measure this metric?  We calculate
how many complaints were filed per 10,000 claims.
So let's
see how many complaints were there about this company?
Total complaints registered related to claims during the entire financial year were
719.
What were the total claims?  349823
claims.  Now you will notice here that
this number of claims and complaints
includes all the categories.  This includes all the
claims filed with this general insurance company across
all categories.
Because the health insurance
related claims were around Rs 12 lakh.  So,
we assume that almost one third of the complaints and claims are
related to health insurance.  Because separate
health insurance or separate category wise
complaints data is not available.
Complaints data
is combined across all categories.  So we will try to guess from this.
Total complaints received are 719 and
total claims are 3449823.
Now how many of these complaints were
accepted?
410 complaints were fully accepted.
I complained that I should get the claim.
So the company accepted 2410 complaints
and paid the money.  671
complaints were partially accepted.  That means the
company accepted approximately 3000 complaints
fully or partially.  374
complaints were rejected and still there are
pending complaints at the end of this
financial year.  When this document was presented, when this
data was reported.  If we calculate this number for
10,000 claims, then the total
complaints come to almost 21
complaints.  21 complaints per 10,000
claims.  If you
talk about industry average, then we will see this year's industry
average after this series.  Which will be the
grand finale in which we will compare all the companies.
We will see in that.
But in the past year claims data, the
average number of complaints was between 20 to 30.
This is less than them.  That's why we have
kept it in the average category.  Because if there were
fewer complaints, this status could have improved.
But here I would like to share one of my personal
observations with you which
I find quite surprising.  Especially in
complaints related to health insurance claims.  The company has accepted a total of 3000
complaints i.e. almost 40% of the complaints.  The
policy
holder got the money.  But I do
not understand that the company took a wrong decision, that is,
they should have got this claim in the beginning itself
but the company did not
give it.  This money was given after the complaint. What negative impact has this
wrong decision had on the company due to the
problems faced by the policy holder
?
That means some penalty may have been imposed or
their grading may have been reduced.  There should be some standard
that if a company rejects a valid claim and
later that claim is
approved, then some fine should be imposed.
If a player makes a mistake or commits a foul in a game,
he is
shown penalty cards so that he does
not repeat the same mistake again.  If you are giving any competitive exam and
negative marking is used in it, then if
you make a mistake,
your marks will be deducted.  But
here the insurance company is openly
taking wrong decisions.  But no
penalty is imposed on this.  At least, the
company may give some discount in the renewal premium to those policy holders who have received this claim money after the complaint
or there may be some other way
so that these insurance companies
take very seriously the fact that which claim they are
rejecting?  Why are they doing this and
they should take this decision very seriously so that there are
minimum chances of mistakes with the policy holders.
Secondly, I would like to say one more thing.
Total complaints are 719.
Does everyone complain?
Only three to four out of 10 people resort to complaint.  The
rest
[sound of clearing throat] people
either criticize the company on social media or
they don't know
how to complain or they don't believe
that these companies will pay.  So if all the
complaints were registered then this number of
accepted complaints could have been even higher.
What is your opinion about this?   Please do let
me know by commenting.  Our fifth and
final metric comes friends, claim
settlement speed.  That is, within what time were all the
health insurance claims filed during the entire year
settled.  So
the data shows that almost 100% of the
claims were settled within a month.
These claims were settled within a month.  The total
number of claims settled within a month was
claims.  Some other claims took one to three
months.  The number is 2529.
Some claims took three to six months.
Only 53 claims and
only two claims went between 6 to 12 months.  That means
almost 100% claims will be settled within a month.  The
company took a lot of time for many claims.  This ratio
shows us the percentage of how
speedily the company is settling the claims.  Now we have given some weightage to the
ratios of these five metrics that we have derived.
25 marks out of total 100 score for claim
settlement ratio.  There
is a weightage of 25% for the claims paid ratio.  The weightage of complaints has been
kept at 20%.  That means if there are very few
complaints then you will get full 20 marks.
Settlement speed i.e. how quickly
claims are settled has a 15% weightage and the
Incurred Claim Ratio also has a 15% weightage.
70% weightage is given to how the customers'
claim experience has been.  According to this
weightage, the total score that this
company has got and if we add it,
then the composite score is 83.8 i.e.
almost 84 out of 100 and the overall grade that the
company has got is very good.  But
if a company
performs exceptionally and its composite score is
higher, then it will be given the grade of A+, that is, the
excellent category,
and if a company does not perform well, then it will be given
B+, B+C. Similarly, there are lower
grades as well, which
we will see in the upcoming videos on the basis of their performance.
After looking at all this data, I
understood that ICICI LBD is
performing very well.  Be it the number of
claims to be settled, the amount to be paid for the claims
, the speed of claim settlement or the
number of complaints, all these are
manageable now.  But as their scores
show, there is still room for improvement.
Things can be improved.
Complaints can also be further reduced.
What is your opinion about this data
?  Please do let me know by commenting.  And
also tell me which insurance company's video do
you want to see in the next Health Insurance Report Card 2026 series,
whose video I will
explain to you in such simple language and yes
I had promised you
a surprise at the end of the video, so congratulations for
staying with me till the end of the video, thank you
very much for this, the surprise for you is that
you will get the PDF summary document of this entire claims data review
in the description.  You can
download this complete document by clicking on the link.  In
which all these metrics and
all this data are shown and along with it, the
method by which companies are ranked and graded is
also mentioned.  If you
liked this video information then do not forget to
like the video and
subscribe to the channel to show your love and support.  I am
Harvinder Singh, I will meet you in the next video.
Till then take care, stay fit and stay
healthy.  Victory.